<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tes irenes trophæa, or, The tryumphs of peace that celebrated the solemnity of the right honourable Sir Francis Iones, Knight, at his inauguration into the maioraltie of London, on Monday being the 30. of October, 1620, at the particular cost and charge of the right worshipfull and ancient Society of the Haberdashers / with explication of the seuerall shewes and deuices by I.S.</title>
            <author>Squire, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23120.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2905</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">29426087</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 29426087</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27962</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12813)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27962)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1858:47)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tes irenes trophæa, or, The tryumphs of peace that celebrated the solemnity of the right honourable Sir Francis Iones, Knight, at his inauguration into the maioraltie of London, on Monday being the 30. of October, 1620, at the particular cost and charge of the right worshipfull and ancient Society of the Haberdashers / with explication of the seuerall shewes and deuices by I.S.</title>
                  <author>Squire, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[19] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes music.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Squire by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Guildhall Library (London, England)</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jones, Francis, --  Sir, fl. 1620.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27962:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27962:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Tes Irenes Trophaea. <hi>OR,</hi> The Tryumphs of Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Celebrated the Solemnity of the</hi> right Honorable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Francis Iones</hi> Knight, at his Inauguration into the Maioraltie <hi>of London, on Monday being the</hi> 30. <hi>of</hi> October, 1620.</p>
            <p>At the particular coſt and charge of the right <hi>worſhipfull and ancient Society of</hi> the Haberdaſhers.</p>
            <p>With explication of the ſeuerall ſhewes and deuices by <hi>I. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <bibl>Vir.</bibl> 
               <q xml:lang="lat">Parua ſub ingentimatris ſe ſubijcit vmbra.</q>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <q xml:lang="lat">IN DOMINO CONFIDO</q>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by NICHOLAS OKES, 1620.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:27962:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27962:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND worthy Gentleman, Sir Francis Iones,</hi> Knight, <hi>Lord Maior of the Citty</hi> of London.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Doubt it is my <hi>Fortune,</hi> to hazard calumny, in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of my inuention in your ſeruice, and not the thing, but the perſon incurs it, whoſe <hi>minority</hi> admits cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure before tryall; therefore I beſeech your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> ſeriouſly to ſuperuiſe this ſlight labour, ſcarce meriting your attention; and the content you want in this, let it be but added to the pleaſure (I hope) your <hi>Honor</hi> will conceiue at view of thoſe reall <hi>Tryumphs</hi> (ſcarce admitting a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond) which your liberall <hi>Society</hi> haue ſo nobly
<pb facs="tcp:27962:3"/> beſtowed on you and then I doubt not but to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt that credite, which many will <hi>Enuy.</hi> Thus wiſhing that the <hi>Tryumphs of Peace</hi> may for euer attend you, I remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honors ſeruant <hi>Io. Squire.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="celebratory_pageant">
            <pb facs="tcp:27962:3"/>
            <head>Tes Irenes Trophaea. <hi>OR,</hi> The Triumphs of Peace.</head>
            <div n="1" type="presentation">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt ſhew, or preſentment, on the water, was a <hi>Chariot,</hi> apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contriued of two ſea <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> Argent, and drawn by two <hi>Sea-horſes,</hi> ſet alſo off with pure ſiluer: on this chariot was one borne repreſenting <hi>Oceanus</hi> his head wreath'd with ſegges, one hand graſping a <hi>ſcepter</hi> of green reeds, to ſhew his potent ſway with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his watery dominions; and the other curbing the forward fearceneſſe of his <hi>horſes:</hi> his azure locks, and beard, o're growne, hung like the careles emblem of a reuerend age, diſheuered or'e his naked limmes, which were ſhadowed off with a mantle of ſea
<pb facs="tcp:27962:4"/> greene taffaty, lymd with waues and fiſhes. This firſt preſentment vſhered on a ſtately well built <hi>ſhip,</hi> bearing full ſaile, figuring the traffique or trade of the (worthy to be eſteemed noble) company of the <hi>Haberdaſhers.</hi> Behind the <hi>ſhippe</hi> ſate <hi>Aeolus</hi> the god of <hi>Winds,</hi> filling their ſailes with proſperous <hi>guſts,</hi> and at each corner of the <hi>ſhip</hi> ſate (vpon ſmall <hi>Ilands)</hi> the 4 parts of the <hi>World, Aſia, Africa, America,</hi> and <hi>Europa,</hi> each of them inuiting their trade vnto their coaſts. <hi>Aſia</hi> was attired in an antique habit of peach coloured Sattin, and buskins of the ſame, a Coronet on her head, and a cenſor in her hand reaking with <hi>Panchayian</hi> ſpices: <hi>Africa</hi> a <hi>blackmoore</hi> in a naked <hi>ſhape,</hi> adorned with <hi>beads,</hi> and in her hand the branch of a <hi>Nut-megg-tree: America</hi> a tawny Moore, vpon her head a crowne of <hi>feathers,</hi> and baſes of the ſame; at her backe, a quiuer of ſhafts, and in her hand a <hi>Parthian bow: Europa</hi> in a robe of <hi>Crymſon</hi> taffaty, on her head an imperiall crowne conferred on her by the other three as <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe</hi> of the <hi>earth,</hi> and holding in her hand a cluſter of grapes, 'to ſignifie her full ſwolne plenty. Theſe meeting the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> on the <hi>Thames</hi> at <hi>three Cranes wharfe,</hi> where he tooke water, <hi>Oceanus</hi> made this ſpeech.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The ſpeech of <hi>Oceanus.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I</hi> that am <hi>ſtil'd</hi> the potent king of <hi>waues,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Oceanus,</hi> he that in a moment can</l>
                           <l>Curbe the vaſt depth of ſea when as it raues,</l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:27962:4"/>
                           <l> And leuell marble mountaines that haue ran,</l>
                           <l>To ruine earth and skies; I now am ſent</l>
                           <l>From all the <hi>watery deities</hi> to attend</l>
                           <l>Thy ſtately <hi>triumphs,</hi> as an honor ment</l>
                           <l>To adde vnto thy greatneſſe, which to'th end,</l>
                           <l>And confines of our rule hath clapt his wings;</l>
                           <l>For ſtill the water <hi>Nymphs,</hi> and <hi>gods</hi> of <hi>ſtreames,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Running vnto my boſom, each one brings,</l>
                           <l>Report of thee; but my beloued <hi>Thames,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Full often when the cheerefull <hi>Lampe</hi> of <hi>day,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Hath warm'd my chilly bowells with his fires,</l>
                           <l>Hath tic'd me from his comfort with a <hi>lay</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Of what thou art; and then with prayers, deſires,</l>
                           <l>And what elſe could attract me to conſent,</l>
                           <l>Hath yeelded to my conuay thy large <hi>ſhips,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>To traffique through my wide vaſt continent.</l>
                           <l>And now with a deſire that outſtrips</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Imagination,</hi> I am come to ſee,</l>
                           <l>And wonder at the <hi>ſtate</hi> which I now find,</l>
                           <l>For to attend thy <hi>Brotherhood,</hi> and <hi>thee:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>And now with you this le<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>gue I will combind,</l>
                           <l>That while the influence of the forked moone,</l>
                           <l>Appoints my curled billowes ebbes, and tides,</l>
                           <l>While that the ſhipman throwes to heauen his boone</l>
                           <l>For ſafe returne, and while that <hi>ſtella</hi> rides,</l>
                           <l>With ſparkling glory o're my wrinkled face,</l>
                           <l>My care ſhall be for euer to attend;</l>
                           <l>Your wealthy bottoms to your coaſts apace;</l>
                           <l>And this my promiſe will I neuer end,</l>
                           <l>Nor breake, vntill your wealth and ſtates ſurmount<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Tagus</hi> vnualued ſands in the account.</l>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27962:5"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The ſpeech of <hi>Aeolus.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <l>ANd here the god of winds his promiſe plights,</l>
                           <l>That whilſt the boiſterous <hi>North,</hi> &amp; gentle <hi>Weſt,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>The <hi>South,</hi> and nipping <hi>Eaſt</hi> wind, daies and nights,</l>
                           <l>Begirt the deſert <hi>Ocean,</hi> ready preſt,</l>
                           <l>To execute my will, with proſperous gales,</l>
                           <l>I will ſend home your <hi>ſhips,</hi> and take delight</l>
                           <l>To play with gentle murmures on your ſailes.</l>
                           <l>Thus ſince both <hi>ſeas,</hi> and <hi>winds,</hi> themſelues vnite,</l>
                           <l>Vnto your <hi>good,</hi> I wiſh all powers <hi>diuine,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Might vnto your their <hi>loue</hi> and aids incline.</l>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="presentation">
               <p>THe ſecond and laſt preſentment on the water, was <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> mount, whereon the nine <hi>Muſes</hi> ſate; <hi>Clyo</hi> the firſt ſuted in a gowne of purple taffaty, and ſtudiouſly imployd in turning ouer <hi>bookes,</hi> ſhee being the <hi>Hiſtoricall</hi> Muſe; <hi>Melpomene</hi> was attired in a blacke taffaty robe, her head deckt with <hi>Cypreſſe,</hi> and playing on a <hi>Theorbo; Thalia</hi> the comick <hi>Muſe</hi> in a light changeable taffaty robe, and playing on a Voyall; <hi>Euterpe</hi> the <hi>Muſe</hi> that firſt inuented wind-inſtruments, was richly apparelled, and playd on a Flute recorder; <hi>Terpſichore</hi> on the <hi>Lute;</hi> and the geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricall Muſe, <hi>Erato</hi> with a ſcale and compaſſe in her hand. The Heroicall Muſe <hi>Calliope</hi> was ſhap't in a tauny ſilke robe, and her temples girt with <hi>Bayes:</hi> the heauenly Muſe <hi>Vrania</hi> that inuented <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> was deckt in a robe of azure taffaty ſemined with <hi>ſtarres;</hi> on her head ſhee wore a coronet of ſtarres,
<pb facs="tcp:27962:5"/> and her right hand ſupported a ſpheare; <hi>Polymneia</hi> the inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres of <hi>Rhethorique</hi> aſſumed her place neereſt to <hi>Apollo,</hi> who ſate on the top of the mount in a robe of cloth of gold, vnder a laurell tree, playing on a harpe, alluding to that of <hi>Virgill:</hi>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">In medio reſidens complectitur omnia <hi>Phoebus.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And on the backſide of the mount ſtood <hi>Mercury</hi> liſtning to their harmonious ſtraines. This accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> vp to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> with varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of muſique, where while his Honor was taking the <hi>Oath,</hi> it returned backe and met him in <hi>Paules Church-yard,</hi> where <hi>Euterpe</hi> &amp; <hi>Terpſichore,</hi> entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him with this ſong.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27962:6"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                  <body>
                     <p> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> We Muſes of the pleaſant hill, that bath within the Theſpian ſpring, That did direct the Grecians quill, Who of olde <hi>Pelius</hi> ſonne did ſing.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> We that <hi>Amphion</hi> did in╌ſpire, With ad╌mired ſtraines and layes, And did infuſe a ſacred fire, In both theſe to gaine the Bayes.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:27962:6"/>
                     <p> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> We <hi>Appolloes</hi> hand-mayds nine, Come to meet thee on the way, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy honours ſhrine, Wee might dedi╌cate this day.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> And his die╌ty vs a╌mong, So curiouſ╌ly ſhal wreſt thy glory. That the enuious mongſt this throng ſhall confeſſe it merits ſtory.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="presentation">
               <pb facs="tcp:27962:7"/>
               <p>THE third preſentment was a Quadrangle, that mounted by aſcents to the forme of an <hi>Egyptian pyramed,</hi> whereon in a well wrought <hi>Landskip,</hi> where figured the ſeuerall ſhieres of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> on the top ſat a princely <hi>Maieſty</hi> acootered in a robe of purple veluet furred with <hi>Ermines,</hi> on his head hee wore an Imperiall Crowne, and in his right hand a <hi>ſcepter;</hi> ouer his head were fixt the armes of <hi>England,</hi> and at his feete a <hi>Lyon</hi> couchant, which did demonſtrate his power in reconciling fearceneſſe vnto a willing ſeruitude; vnder him ſate two <hi>Dukes;</hi> two <hi>Marquiſes;</hi> two <hi>Earles,</hi> and two <hi>Barons,</hi> in <hi>Parliament robes</hi> of purple veluet; about their neckes they wore collers of <hi>Eſſes,</hi> and on their heads the apt cognizance of each ones honor; at the 4 corners of this <hi>Pyramed,</hi> ſtood two <hi>Lyons, Or,</hi> and two <hi>Vnicornes Argent,</hi> ſupporting 4 <hi>ſtreamers,</hi> wherein were Eſcutchoned the armes of our foure <hi>Kingdomes, England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was caractered in a ſcroule, <hi>Respublica Beata;</hi> and round about it ran the <hi>Ocean.</hi> This <hi>Pyramed</hi> was ſupported by foure ſiluer <hi>Corinthian</hi> columnes, the <hi>Baſes,</hi> and <hi>Capitalls,</hi> fine gold. Within theſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnes ſate 4 Perſons, that ſeemed as it were to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derprop the ponderous burthen of the <hi>Pyramed;</hi> the firſt was the <hi>Citty,</hi> preſented in a ſcarlet gowne gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with blacke Veluet, like a Lady <hi>Maiores;</hi> and in her hand two golden <hi>keyes;</hi> the other the Country in a <hi>Ruſtique habit;</hi> the third the <hi>Law,</hi> habited like a <hi>Iudge,</hi> and a ſcrowle in his hand; the fourth <hi>Religion</hi> in a <hi>rotchet</hi> like a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and in his hand a <hi>booke.</hi> At
<pb facs="tcp:27962:7"/> the 4 corners of this vnder ſquare ſtood two <hi>Lyons Or,</hi> and two <hi>Gotes, Argent,</hi> which are the ſupporters of the <hi>Companies Armes,</hi> bearing 4 large <hi>ſtreamers,</hi> in which were the armes of the <hi>Citty,</hi> and of the <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;</hi> and in the front ſtood the creſt of the <hi>Lord Maior,</hi> a <hi>Lyon</hi> ſupporting an azure <hi>anchor,</hi> and on it was fixt his cote of <hi>Armes,</hi> which was a chiefe <hi>Or,</hi> with a <hi>Lyon Or,</hi> vpon a <hi>field azure,</hi> betweene 3 <hi>croſt formes Or.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="presentation">
               <p>THE fourth preſentment, being the maine Pageant, was a Mount, where on the top vnder a canopie lim'd with ſtarres, was ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Catherin,</hi> the <hi>Saint</hi> of the <hi>Company,</hi> whom antique ſtories report to be the daughter of <hi>Coſtus</hi> King of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> ſhe was attired in a ſnow white ſattin gowne, in one hand ſhe held a <hi>booke,</hi> and in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>ſword</hi> with the point downeward; it being the inſtrument that in death ſealed her the fruition of immortall reſt; her head circuled with a crowne of <hi>gold,</hi> which did intimate her <hi>princely</hi> deſcent; and at her feete lay a broken <hi>wheele:</hi> round about ſate her <hi>Attendants</hi> twelue maydes of honor gorgeouſly attired, each one bearing in her hand a <hi>ſiluer ſheild,</hi> vpon which were portrayed <hi>Catherin Wheeles,</hi> and within them the <hi>Motto</hi> to the <hi>Companies armes, Serue and obay.</hi> Vnder theſe ſate her ſeruants at worke, ſome carding <hi>Wooll;</hi> ſome <hi>Spinning;</hi> others <hi>Knitting capps;</hi> with her <hi>Feltmakers;</hi> one <hi>Bowed;</hi> one <hi>Baſoned;</hi> and another <hi>Blockt;</hi> and behind the Mount ſate a <hi>Shepheard</hi> keeping his <hi>ſheepe:</hi> Each of which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious
<pb facs="tcp:27962:8"/> faculties haue reference to the <hi>ſupport</hi> of this Worſhipfull <hi>Society.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="presentation">
               <p>THE fifth and laſt inuention, was a Chariot painted full with <hi>houre-glaſſes,</hi> and <hi>ſun-dialls,</hi> the fore-wheeles were two <hi>Globes,</hi> and the hinder wheeles were like two Church <hi>dialls;</hi> within it aged <hi>Time</hi> was drawne, ſeated vpon an <hi>houre-glaſſe</hi> that was ſupported on the ſhoulders of a gyant, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the <hi>Iron age;</hi> in one hand he held a <hi>ſickle,</hi> in the other a <hi>croutch;</hi> and in the <hi>Chariot</hi> with him were drawne the foure <hi>Elements, Ignis, Aer, Aqua,</hi> and <hi>Terra. Ignis</hi> fire, was attired in a flame coloured taffaty robe, leaning on a <hi>Salamander,</hi> and in his hand three teend Lightning; <hi>Aer</hi> Aire, in a robe lymmed with clouds and ſeuerall ſhaps of <hi>Birds,</hi> and in his hand a <hi>Doue; Aqua</hi> water, in a robe limmed with <hi>Waues</hi> and <hi>Fiſhes,</hi> her azure treſſes deckt with flegges, and in her hand a veſſell full of liue <hi>Fiſhes; Terra</hi> earth, in a robe on which graſſe and flowers, ſprang as it were naturally; on her head ſtood green corne, and in her hand ſhe bare a <hi>ſiluer ſpade.</hi> This Chariot was drawne by the foure <hi>ſeaſons</hi> of the yeare, <hi>Ver</hi> the <hi>ſpring, Aeſtas</hi> the <hi>ſommer, Antumne,</hi> and <hi>Hyems winter. Ver</hi> was ſuted in greene taffaty, a chaplet of flowers on her head, a bow in her hand and a quiuer at her backe like a huntreſſe; <hi>Aeſtas</hi> in a yellow taffaty robe, and her browes like <hi>Ceres,</hi> deckt with ripe corne, &amp; a cornucopiae in her hand; <hi>Autumne</hi> in a naked ſhape like <hi>Bacchus,</hi> his temples wreathed with vines, and in his hand a cluſter of <hi>grapes; Hyems Winter</hi> in a furred gowne, and in his hand a pan of burning coles. This Chariot, in the
<pb facs="tcp:27962:8"/> euening when the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> came to <hi>Paules,</hi> at the vpper Conduit in Cheapeſide, <hi>Time</hi> made this ſpeech.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <l>ME thinkes I ſee amazement pierce each eye,</l>
                           <l>That viewes me repreſenting my weake ſtate,</l>
                           <l>Who ſated with my dull variety,</l>
                           <l>Turne backe their heads I do not imitate;</l>
                           <l>But ſhew the ſpatious world, the age I beare:</l>
                           <l>For when command of the immortall powers,</l>
                           <l>Had giuen me being, when I firſt did reare</l>
                           <l>My Nimble eſſence on the winged howers:</l>
                           <l>I went forth like the ſpring, and did behold,</l>
                           <l>And weare out mans firſt dayes the age of gold;</l>
                           <l>Then roſe the ſiluer age, and that decaid<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Succeſſiuely</hi> another ganne to raigne,</l>
                           <l>Called the Brazen age: when that did fade,</l>
                           <l>This laſt prop of the world that doth ſuſtaine,</l>
                           <l>My ponderous glaſſe and me, the Iron age,</l>
                           <l>Sprung vp to be my <hi>Atlas;</hi> were he gone,</l>
                           <l>Theſe <hi>Elements</hi> attending would with rage,</l>
                           <l>Turne feeble <hi>Time</hi> to deſolation:</l>
                           <l>But now doe you not wonder much to ſee,</l>
                           <l>Me as I am ay'd, a ſolemnity,</l>
                           <l>Like to a victor borne triumphantly?</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>O Honord Lord,</hi> it is to ſhew the loue,</l>
                           <l>I bare to thee and thy Societie,</l>
                           <l>Whoſe bounteous intertainments are aboue</l>
                           <l>All that I euer found. Now in returne,</l>
                           <l>I promiſe this, if that with <hi>honor'd</hi> care,</l>
                           <l>Thou execute thy charge, then ſhall thy vrne,</l>
                           <l>Be reuerenced, and thither ſhall repaire,</l>
                           <l>A bleſſed <hi>memory</hi> that neuer dies,</l>
                           <l>To bl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſon it vnto poſterities.</l>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:27962:9"/>
               <p> Vnder this <hi>Pyramed,</hi> ſate ſacred <hi>Peace,</hi> that chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged her celeſtiall Manſion, to make vs happy with the ſweete pleaſures of a quiet ſtate; on her head ſhe wore a wreath of oliues, in her right hand a palme, her robe was of white taffaty, limm'd with the mappe of <hi>England:</hi> in her lap ſhee bare the modell of <hi>London,</hi> and on her left arme a ſheild, whereon was <hi>Vndae Argent and azure</hi> vpon a bend <hi>Gules</hi> a <hi>Lyon paſſant gardant Or,</hi> the Armes of the Societie; at her feete lay warre in compleat armes vpon Speares, Launces, foulded enſignes; and leaning on <hi>an Vnbrac't drum;</hi> this ſhew paſſed along till the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> came to <hi>Saint Laurence</hi> lane end, where <hi>Peace</hi> began to ſpeake thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The ſpeech of <hi>Peace.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <l>
                              <hi>A</hi> Welcome honor'd <hi>Pretor</hi> I doc giue,</l>
                           <l>Free and vnbounded, as my wiſh to liue,</l>
                           <l>And to retaine the bleſſed <hi>ſtiles</hi> are giuen</l>
                           <l>Me, with applauſe of <hi>Nations</hi> and of heauen:</l>
                           <l>From whence I boaſt my linage; I am <hi>Peace</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>That my long <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> did neuer ceaſe,</l>
                           <l>From the firſt minute of the aged <hi>World,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Vntill I found this <hi>Iland;</hi> for being hurld</l>
                           <l>Out of each region by rebellious <hi>War,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>(Which now lies bound my <hi>Vaſſall)</hi> like a <hi>ſtar,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Whoſe vnfixt glory glides from ſpheare, to ſpheare,</l>
                           <l>I wandred vp and downe: and not a teare</l>
                           <l>I ſhed, but with it went a ſigh that I</l>
                           <l>Might be ſo fauor'd of the <hi>Deity,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:27962:9"/>
                           <l> To be recald from earth, which when they ſaw</l>
                           <l>Me, from the world be ſides they did withdraw,</l>
                           <l>To this (then troubled) <hi>ſtate,</hi> which did imbrace</l>
                           <l>Me with ſuch <hi>Ioy,</hi> that <hi>Nobles</hi> flockt apace,</l>
                           <l>To intertaine me, and the <hi>poore</hi> did ſtand,</l>
                           <l>To craue my <hi>bleſſing,</hi> to ore flowe their land;</l>
                           <l>And <hi>Ioyntly</hi> all of them deliuered <hi>War,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Fetterd in chaines to be my <hi>priſoner,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Now honord <hi>Lord</hi> ſince that you find and ſee,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Peace</hi> placed here by a <hi>diuine</hi> decree;</l>
                           <l>Within this <hi>common-wealth,</hi> and chiefely here,</l>
                           <l>Within this <hi>Citty,</hi> where for one whole yeare,</l>
                           <l>Thy <hi>mandats</hi> are obayd, then haue a care,</l>
                           <l>To ſee me <hi>ſafely</hi> kept; and ſince you beare</l>
                           <l>That powerfull <hi>ſway</hi> about yee that attends,</l>
                           <l>The execution of your will, and ends:</l>
                           <l>Imploy't ſo nobly that my <hi>generall ſtate,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>May ſay thou leadſt the way to imitate.</l>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>After the Sermon at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  </hi> Paules Church <hi>was ended, the</hi> Lord Maior <hi>returned backe by torch light to his houſe, attended by the whole body of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, where being come to his gate,</hi> War <hi>from out the</hi> Pageant <hi>called the</hi> Common-wealth, <hi>made this ſpeech.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <l>IT is decreed, nor can my power reſiſt,</l>
                           <l>This moſt incuitable doombe of fate,</l>
                           <l>I haue forgot my nature, and conſiſt</l>
                           <l>Of ſomething more then lenity: my ſtate,</l>
                           <l>At firſt was ſoueraignty; and that ſame ſway,</l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:27962:10"/>
                           <l> That curb'd dominions: for I mounted on</l>
                           <l>The backe of horror, bath'd in blood, could fray</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Peace</hi> from their coaſts, then deſolation,</l>
                           <l>I could command to raiſe my ſtatues there,</l>
                           <l>That <hi>Nations far</hi> remote with mourning eies,</l>
                           <l>Should not rehearſe the ſtory without feare,</l>
                           <l>Leſt I might ſo cloſe vp their obſequies:</l>
                           <l>I taught the <hi>Romans</hi> to immortallize,</l>
                           <l>Their names by their great acts, and to refine,</l>
                           <l>Their meane creation by the ſacrifize,</l>
                           <l>Of their owne blood to <hi>Warre</hi> and to my ſhrine,</l>
                           <l>They offer'd mighty ſpoyles, but now I beare</l>
                           <l>Captiuity about me: yet like one</l>
                           <l>That renders ſeruitude for loue, nor feare,</l>
                           <l>Imploying his deuotion to be ſhowne,</l>
                           <l>As free as if his mind could captiuate</l>
                           <l>His will, I yeeld to ſacred <hi>Peace</hi> and you;</l>
                           <l>That this day haue with a tryumphant ſtate,</l>
                           <l>Entred your charge, and office, which the <hi>due</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Of <hi>Time</hi> admitts you too, and ſhould it chance,</l>
                           <l>That any foraigne armes from out this throane,</l>
                           <l>Striue to inforce her, I will then aduance,</l>
                           <l>My enſignes to her aide; and make it knowne,</l>
                           <l>That this is her inheritance, and place,</l>
                           <l>Which heauen hath pointed out to be her reſt;</l>
                           <l>And therefore worthy <hi>Lord</hi> follow the trace</l>
                           <l>Of noble <hi>preſidents,</hi> and in thy breſt,</l>
                           <l>Reſolue of future hazards; and prepare</l>
                           <l>Me ſuch prouiſions that if times ſhould ceaſe,</l>
                           <l>To be vnto this land is now they are,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Warre</hi> might reſtore againe the Palme to <hi>Peace.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:27962:10"/>
               <p> This ſpeech being ended, <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Warre</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted from vnder the <hi>Pyramed, Peace</hi> conducted the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> into his houſe; and <hi>Warre</hi> ſtood with fire and ſword to defend his gates.</p>
               <p>And thus the ſolemnity diſſolued.</p>
               <p>The credit of this workmanſhip (curiouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding many former ſhewes, and far more ritch then any, in regard no mettall was vſed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne it but gold and ſiluer) I impoſe on <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Tipſley</hi> Cittizen and <hi>Haberdaſher</hi> of <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
